How's your blog going?
Yeah, good, very good.
You haven't written a word, have you?
You just wrote
"still has trust issues".
And you read my writing upside down.
You see what I mean?
John, you're a soldier
and it's going to take you
a while to adjust to civilian life
and writing a blog
about everything that happens to you
will honestly help you.
Nothing happens to me.
'What do you mean there's no ruddy
car?' He went to Waterloo, I'm sorry.
Get a cab! I never get cabs!
I love you. When?
Get a cab!
My husband
was a happy man
lived life to the full.
He loved his family and his work,
and that he should have
taken his own life in this way
is a mystery
and a shock to all who knew him.
Taxi, taxi!
I'll be just two minutes, mate.
What?
I'm just going home to get
my umbrella. You can share mine.
Two minutes, all right?
She still dancing?
Yeah, if you can call it that.
Did you get the car keys off her?
Got them out of her bag.
Where is she?
The body of Beth Davenport,
Junior Minister for Transport,
was found late last night
on a building site in Greater London.
Preliminary investigations
suggest that this was suicide.
We can confirm that this apparent
suicide closely resembles those of
Sir Jeffrey Patterson
and James Phillimore.
In the light of this, these incidents
are now being treated as linked.
The investigation is ongoing
but Detective Inspector Lestrade
will take questions now.
Detective Inspector,
how can suicides be linked?
Well, they all took the same poison.
They were all found in places
they had no reason to be.
None of them had shown any prior
indication. But you can't have
serial suicides.
Well, apparently you can.
These three people,
there's nothing that links them?
There's no link we've found yet but
we're looking for it.
There has to be one.
If you've all got texts, please
ignore them. It just says "Wrong".
Well, just ignore that.
If there are no more questions,
I'm going to bring
this session to an end.
If they're suicides,
what are you investigating?
As I say, these suicides
are clearly linked.
It's an unusual situation, we've
got our best people investigating.
Says "Wrong" again.
One more question. Is there any
chance that these are murders?
And if they are, is this
the work of a serial killer?
I know that you like
writing about these but these
do appear to be suicides.
We know the difference. The poison
was clearly self-administered.
Yes, but if they are murders,
how do people keep themselves safe?
Well, don't commit suicide.
Daily Mail!
This is a frightening time
for people but all anyone has to do
is exercise reasonable precautions.
We are all as safe as we want to be.
MOBILE PHONES BUZZ
Thank you.
You've got to stop him doing that.
He's making us look like idiots.
If you can tell me
how he does it, I'll stop him.
John!
John Watson!
Stamford, Mike Stamford.
We were at Barts together.
Yes, sorry, yes, Mike, hello.
Yes, I know, I got fat. No, no.
I heard you were abroad somewhere
getting shot at. What happened?
I got shot.
Are you still at Barts then?
Teaching now, yeah, bright
young things like we used to be.
God, I hate them.
What about you, just staying in
town till you get yourself sorted?
I can't afford London
on an Army pension.
Couldn't bear to be anywhere else.
That's not the John Watson I know.
I'm not the John Watson.
Couldn't Harry help?
Yeah, like that's going to happen(!)
I don't know,
get a flatshare or something?
Who'd want me for a flatmate?
What?
You're the second person
to say that to me today.
Who was the first?
How fresh?
Just in. 67, natural causes.
Used to work here.
I knew him, he was nice.
Fine.
We'll start with the riding crop.
So, bad day was it?
I need to know what bruises
form in the next 20 minutes.
A man's alibi depends on it. Text me.
Listen, I was wondering.
Maybe later, when you're finished...
You're wearing lipstick.
You weren't wearing lipstick before.
I refreshed it a bit.
Sorry, you were saying?
I was wondering
if you'd like to have coffee?
Black, two sugars, please.
I'll be upstairs.
OK.
KNOCK ON DOOR
Bit different from my day.
You've no idea!
Mike, can I borrow your phone?
There's no signal on mine.
And what's wrong with the landline?
I prefer to text.
Sorry, it's in my coat.
Here, use mine.
Oh, thank you.
This is an old friend of mine,
John Watson.
Afghanistan or Iraq?
Sorry?
Which was it, in Afghanistan or Iraq?
Afghanistan, sorry,
how did you know?
Ah! Coffee, thank you.
What happened to the lipstick?
It wasn't working for me.
Really? It was a big improvement.
Your mouth's too small now.
OK.
How do you feel about the violin?
I'm sorry, what?
I play the violin when I'm thinking
and sometimes I don't talk for days
on end. Would that bother you?
Potential flatmates should know
the worst about each other.
You told him about me? Not a word.
Who said anything about flatmates?
I did. Told Mike this morning
that I must be a difficult man
to find a flatmate for.
Now here he is just after lunch with
an old friend clearly just home from
military service in Afghanistan.
Wasn't a difficult leap.
How did you know about Afghanistan?
Got my eye on a nice little place
in central London.
We ought to be able to afford it.
We'll meet there tomorrow
evening, seven o'clock.
Sorry, got to dash. I think I left
my riding crop in the mortuary.
Is that it?
Is that what?
We've only just met and we're
going to go and look at a flat?
Problem?
We don't know
a thing about each other.
I don't know where we're meeting,
I don't even know your name.
I know you're an Army doctor
and you've been invalided home
from Afghanistan.
You've got a brother worried
about you but you won't go
to him for help because you don't
approve of him, possibly because he's
an alcoholic, more likely because
he recently walked out on his wife.
And I know that your therapist
thinks your limp's psychosomatic,
quite correctly, I'm afraid.
That's enough to be going
on with, don't you think?
The name's Sherlock Holmes
and the address is 221B Baker Street.
Afternoon.
Yeah, he's always like that.
Hello.
Ah - Mr Holmes. Sherlock, please.
Well, this is a prime spot.
Must be expensive.
Mrs Hudson, the landlady -
she's given me a special deal.
Owes me a favour. A few years back,
her husband got himself
sentenced to death in Florida.
I was able to help out. Sorry - you
stopped her husband being executed?
Oh, no, I ensured it.
Sherlock!
Mrs Hudson, Dr John Watson.
Hello. Come in. Thank you.
Shall we...?
Well, this could be very nice.
Very nice indeed.
Yes.
Yes, I think so,
my thoughts precisely.
TOGETHER: So I went straight ahead
and moved in. Soon as we get all this
rubbish cleaned out...
So this is all... Well, obviously I
can erm...straighten things up a bit.
That's a skull. Friend of mine.
When I say friend...
What do you think, then, Dr Watson?
There's another bedroom upstairs,
if you'll be needing two bedrooms.
Of course we'll be needing two.
Oh, don't worry, there's all sorts
round here. Mrs Turner next door's
got (married ones).
Oh...
Sherlock! The mess you've made.
I looked you up on
the internet last night.
Anything interesting? Found your
website. The Science of Deduction.
What did you think?
You said you could identify
a software designer by his tie and
an airline pilot by his left thumb?
Yes.
And I can read your military career
in your face and your leg,
and your brother's drinking habits
on your mobile phone.
How?
What about these suicides then,
Sherlock? I thought that'd be
right up your street.
Three exactly the same.
Four.
There's been a fourth.
And there's something different
this time. A fourth?
Where? Brixton, Lauriston Gardens.
What's new about this one? You
wouldn't have come to me otherwise.
You know how they never leave notes?
Yeah. This one did.
Will you come?
Who's on forensics? Anderson.
He doesn't work well with me.
Well, he won't be your assistant.
I NEED an assistant.
Will you come? Not in a police car,
I'll be right behind.
Thank you.
Brilliant! Yes!
Four serial suicides, and now a note.
Oh, it's Christmas. Mrs Hudson,
I'll be late. Might need some food.
I'm your landlady, dear,
not your housekeeper.
Something cold will do. John, have
a cup of tea, make yourself at home.
Don't wait up!
Look at him, dashing about...
My husband was just the same.
But you're more
the sitting-down type, I can tell.
I'll make you that cuppa,
you rest your leg.
Damn my leg! Sorry, I'm so sorry -
It's just sometimes
this bloody thing...
I understand, dear, I've got a hip.
Cup of tea'd be lovely. Thank you.
Just this once, dear,
I'm not your housekeeper.
Couple of biscuits too, if you've
got 'em. Not your housekeeper!
You're a doctor.
In fact you're an Army doctor.
Yes.
Any good?
Very good.
Seen a lot of injuries, then.
Violent deaths.
Well, yes.
Bit of trouble too, I bet?
Of course. Yes.
Enough for a lifetime, far too much.
Want to see some more? Oh, God, yes.
Sorry Mrs Hudson, I'll skip the tea.
Off out. Both of you?
Impossible suicides? Four of them?
No point sitting at home when there's
finally something fun going on!
Look at you, all happy. It's not
decent. Who cares about decent?
The game, Mrs Hudson, is on!
Taxi!
OK, You've got questions...
Yeah, where are we going?
Crime scene. Next?
Who are you, what do you do?
What do you think?
I'd say...private detective. But?
But the police don't go
to private detectives.
I'm a consulting detective. Only
one in the world, I invented the job.
What does that mean? Means when
the police are out of their depth,
which is always,
they consult me.
The police don't consult amateurs.
When I met you for the first time
yesterday, I said Afghanistan
or Iraq. You looked surprised.
Yes, how DID you know?
I didn't know, I saw.
'Your haircut, the way
you hold yourself says military.
'But your conversation...'
Bit different from my day.
..said trained at Barts -
so Army doctor, obvious.
'Your face is tanned...
'but no tan above the wrists. You've
been abroad, but not sunbathing.
'Your limp's really bad
when you walk, but you don't ask
for a chair when you stand -
'so it's at least partly
psychosomatic.
'That says the original circumstances
of the injury were traumatic -'
wounded in action then. Wounded in
action, suntan - Afghanistan or Iraq.
You said I had a therapist.
You've got a psychosomatic limp,
of course you've got a therapist.
Then there's your brother. Mm?
Your phone.
'It's expensive,
e-mail enabled, MP3 player.'
And you're looking for a flatshare.
You wouldn't buy this - it's a gift.
'Scratches.
Not one, many over time -'
it's been in the same pocket
as keys and coins.
You wouldn't treat
your one luxury item like this,
so it's had a previous owner.
Next bit's easy. You know it already.
The engraving?
Harry Watson. Clearly a family
member who's given you his old phone.
Not your father,
this is a young man's gadget.
Could be a cousin, but you're a war
hero who can't find a place to live -
unlikely you've got an extended
family, not one you're close to.
So brother it is.
Now, who's Clara? Three kisses
says it's a romantic attachment.
The expense of the phone
says wife, not girlfriend.
Must have given it to him recently,
it's only six months old.
Marriage in trouble then -
six months on he's given it away.
If she'd left HIM,
he would have kept it. Sentiment.
No, he wanted rid of it. He left HER.
He gave the phone to you,
so he wants you to stay in touch.
You're looking for cheap
accommodation, but you're not
going to your brother for help -
that says you've got problems
with him. Maybe you liked his wife,
or don't like his drinking.
How can you possibly know
about the drinking?
Shot in the dark. Good one, though.
Power connection -
tiny little scuff marks round it.
Every night he plugs it in
but his hands are shaking.
You never see those marks
on a sober man's phone,
never see a drunk's without them.
There you go, you were right.
I was right? Right about what?
The police don't consult amateurs.
That...was amazing.
Do you think so? Of course it was.
It was extraordinary,
it was quite extraordinary.
That's not what people normally say.
What do people normally say?
Piss off!
Did I get anything wrong?
Harry and me don't get on,
never have,
Clara and Harry split up
three months ago
and they're getting a divorce,
and Harry is a drinker.
Spot on, then. I didn't expect
to be right about everything.
Harry's short for Harriet.
Harry's your sister.
Look, what exactly am I supposed
to be doing here? Sister!
No - seriously, what am I doing
here? There's always something.
Hello, freak! I'm here to see
Detective Inspector Lestrade.
Why?
I was invited.
I think he wants me to take a look.
Well, you know what I think,
don't you? Always Sally.
I even know you didn't
make it home last night.
I don't... Who's this?
Colleague of mine, Dr Watson.
Dr Watson, Sergeant Sally Donovan.
Old friend.
A colleague(?)
How do YOU get a colleague?
Did he follow you home?
Would it be better
if I just waited... No.
Freak's here. Bringing him in.
Ah, Anderson. Here we are again.
It's a crime scene. I don't want it
contaminated. Are we clear on that?
Quite clear.
And is your wife away for long?
Oh, don't pretend you worked
that out. Somebody told you that.
Your deodorant told me that.
My deodorant?
It's for men. Well, of course
it's for men - I'm wearing it.
So's Sergeant Donovan.
Ooh... I think it just vaporised.
May I go in?
Whatever you're trying to imply...
I'm not implying anything. I'm sure
Sally came round for a nice little
chat, and just happened to stay over.
And I assume she scrubbed
your floors, going by
the state of her knees.